Guide to the Cushing and Myra Fairbanks Eells Papers 1838-1938
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Cushing and Myra Fairbanks Eells Papers
1838-1938
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 148
Eells, Cushing, 1810-1893.
0.25 Linear feet of shelf space 1 Box
Correspondence, clippings, poster, and photocopies and transcripts of correspondence by and about the Eells, their missionary work in Oregon and among the Spokane Tribe, and the 1847 Whitman Massacre.
The reminiscences of Cushing Eells are located at Whitman College, but Dr. Drury obtained a typescript transcription in 1938 for Washington State University.
Correspondence, clippings, poster, and photocopies and transcripts of correspondence by and about the Eells, their missionary work in Oregon and among the Spokane Tribe, and the 1847 Whitman Massacre. Of the approximately twenty-five items in this collection, the bulk is of the nature of photocopies and typescript transcripts. However, there is a letter of Mrs. Eells to her sister written in 1853, and a manuscript draft of a diary-like reminiscence of the first month of the Eells' journey west in 1838. This draft has been amended and annotated as if for publication. Much of this material was secured by Clifford M. Drury prior to 1938.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The papers of Cushing and Myra Fairbanks Eells, pioneer missionaries, were procured for the Washington State University Library by Dr. Clifford M. Drury in the course of researching the lives of the Pacific Northwest missionaries.
Elkanah and Mary Richardson Walker Papers, 1830-1938 (Cage 57).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Eells, Cushing, 1810-1893 -- Archives.; Eells, Myra Fairbanks, 1805-1878 -- Archives.; Eells, Myra Fairbanks, 1805-1878.
Missionaries -- Northwest, Pacific -- Correspondence.; Spokane Indians -- Missions.; Whitman Massacre, 1847.; Indians of North America -- Missions -- Northwest, Pacific.
Missionaries; Native Americans; Washington (State); Oregon
- Eells, Myra Fairbanks. Memorandum, journeying, Holden, Mass., 1838 March 6-[1838 March 29]; 2 leaves, manuscript draft with emendations. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Eells, Myra Fairbanks. Letter, Hillsborough, [Oregon] to Dear Sister., 1853 February 23; 2 leaves, holograph signed. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Eells, Myra Fairbanks. "Oregon in 1838; original letter written by Mrs. M. T. Eells, at Walla Walla, October 4, 1838.", 1838 October 4; 1 newspaper clipping. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Unidentified newspaper clipping from the collection of Mrs. Thorburn Ross, Portland, Oregon.
- Eells, Walter Crosby "New letters add to Eells record." Spokesman-Review., 1960 July 31; 1 newspaper clipping. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photocopies of papers of M. F. Eells
  - Memorandum, journeying., 1838 March 6; 4 leaves, manuscript. (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter, Tualatin Academy, to Mrs. Grout, 1850 November 5; 4 leaves, manuscript. (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter, Hillsborough, to Dear Sister., 1853 February 23; 4 leaves, manuscript. (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Reminiscences of Cushing Eells, 1882-1892, a transcript of the Original manuscript at Whitman College., 1938; [99] pages, typescript. Also a photocopy of the transcript. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Transcriptions of correspondence., 1838-1904; 52 leaves, typescript. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Cushing Eells centennial celebration, Chewelah, Washington., 1938 September 18; 1 poster. (Box 1, Folder 8)